Lord Shen,
大阁领
today's welcome banquet
今日的接风宴
is likely to be called off.
怕是吃不成了
Mr. Pan
潘郎君
has uncovered a key figure
发现了无头尸案中的
in the headless corpse case.
重要人物
Who is it?
什么人
His name is Liu Zongyuan,
他叫刘宗远
the neighboring tenant farmer of
是死者李楷祥的
the deceased, Li Kaixiang.
邻家租户
After the incident,
案发之后
I discovered that many of the deceased's
我发现死者不少家田
land had come under his control.
都落入了他手下
So I went to his home to investigate
于是前去家里查探
and found that he
发现这个人
had just moved away recently.
刚刚搬走不久
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
could you please send someone
这衙府可否派些人
to look into his whereabouts?
去查探他的下落
It would be best if we could capture him.
最好能抓回来
OK.
没问题
Lord Commander,
大阁领
I sincerely apologize.
实在是抱歉
This is indeed an unforeseen circumstance.
今日确实是突发情况
I hope you understand, Lord Shen.
还望大阁领海涵
Investigation is of utmost importance,
查案要紧
Lord Mo need not feel guilty.
莫刺史不必自责
Since he left not long ago,
既然他离开没有多久
and it is quite a distance from the city,
距离出城也有一段距离
why not issue a city lockdown order?
不如下一道封城令
I'll have guardsmen intensify the search.
我内卫再一道加强搜查
perhaps we can catch him.
说不定能将此人留下
My lord, you're absolutely correct.
大阁领所言极是
I will instruct Biqiu to draft a
我这就命比丘
city lockdown order immediately.
拟封城令下发
I hope we can soon capture the murderer
希望早日将真凶
and bring him to justice.
缉拿归案
If we can also put an end to the rumors
若是能将半面鬼
about the masked spectre
睡梦中吃人一事的谣言
devouring people in their sleep,
一并破除
that would be even better.
那就再好不过了
I'm afraid I'll be returning late tonight,
今日恐怕晚归
so don't wait for me.
不用等我
Let's get going.
走吧
I'll take my leave.
我先走了
It's still early,
时间还早
how about we pay a visit to Li Kairui
我们去牢里会会李楷瑞
in the jail?
如何
We've scoured all the streets
营州城的大小街道
in the city, but
都已经搜遍
there's still no trace of Liu Zongyuan.
却不见刘宗远的身影
He must have either fled the city
他要么是逃出城去了
or is hiding in some residence
要么还藏匿在城中的
within the city.
某处宅子里
We have already issued orders
我们已经下令
to lock the city gates
封锁了城门
and set up checkpoints along the routes.
沿途还设关卡
The likelihood of Liu Zongyuan
刘宗远
escaping the city
能逃出城的可能性
is very low.
非常小
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
I recommend that
我是建议
we conduct another thorough search of
把嫌犯可能藏匿的院子
the courtyards where he might be hiding.
再搜查一遍
We'd be wise to avoid doing so.
算了吧
The citizens in the city
城内的百姓
are already
本身就因为
feeling uneasy
近日的凶杀案
due to the recent murders.
闹得人心惶惶
If they see the authority
若是再看到官府
searching homes at night,
半夜搜寻民宅
it will only heighten their fears.
恐怕人心不稳啊
You've seen it yourself,
你也看到了
The gates have checkpoints in place.
城门既已设卡
My men will thoroughly inspect everyone.
我的兵会严查进出人员
He won't be able to slip away.
他跑不了的
Go ahead and enter.
进去吧
Next!
下一个
Sign here.
在这儿写
What do you have in your bag?
包里装的什么
The garrison at Yingzhou
营州城的士兵
is indeed well-disciplined
果然军纪严明
and equipped.
不同凡响
It seems the commander has invested ample
想来是主官
effort and resources into the troops.
花了不少心力财力治军
Their breastplates and shoulder guards
他们的胸背甲和护肩
are of outstanding quality,
都十分精良
unlike those of ordinary border soldiers.
不像是普通的边塞士兵
You come from the imperial capital.
你是从皇城来的
You must have seen
优良的军备
plenty of top-notch military equipment.
你可见过不少
These mediocre armors of mine
我这点盔甲
are nothing to boast about.
算不了什么
This city
营州城
is situated on the western frontier,
地处西域边塞
and defense is our top priority!
防卫是重中之重
We are cutting costs wherever possible,
我们是处处节省开支
and all the savings I can muster
我能省下来的银子
are directed towards military supplies.
全花在了军需上
We're quite constrained in this regard.
没办法的事情
Lord Shen,
大阁领
we have located him.
人找到了
This lady
这位
is a scribe from the Ministry of Justice.
是刑部的颜令史
She has some questions for you.
她有些问题要问你
My lady,
令史大人
I'm innocent, my lady!
我是冤枉的 大人
There's no need to plead with me now.
不用着急跟我伸冤
Just answer
我问什么
all my questions.
你答什么便是
As long as you can clear my name,
只要大人能为我伸冤
I'm willing to
让我做什么事情
do anything!
我都愿意
Do you know
刘宗远
Liu Zongyuan?
你认识吗
Yes, he has
认识
a good relationship with my brother.
和我大哥关系不错
On the day of the incident,
出事那天
I had invited him and my brother
我本请了他和大哥
to drink together, but he
一起喝酒
left in the middle due to some business.
可他临时有事便走开了
As a result,
因此
no one can prove
便没人能证明
my innocence!
我的清白啊
Do you know
那他来自哪里
where he is from?
你可知晓
I only know he is a merchant
我只知道他是个商人
and has assisted my brother
在生意上
with business strategies.
还帮过我大哥出谋划策
Does Liu Zongyuan know martial arts?
那刘宗远他会武功吗
No,
不会
he is just a merchant.
他就是个商人
Are you certain?
这么肯定
I remember one time
我记得有一次
a snake entered his house,
他家中跑进了一条蛇
and it was my brother who helped catch it!
还是我大哥帮忙捉的
Lady Yan,
颜令史
what are you jotting down?
你在记什么呢
Just taking some notes.
记录案情而已
And I have a sketch of the masked spectre.
还有一张半面鬼的画像
It's something
是我自己
I drew from my imagination.
凭空所想而画的
So Lady Yan
原来颜令史
has such artistic talent too?
还有此等才能啊
Then let me see
那不妨让我看看
what this masked spectre
在你心中这半面鬼
looks like in your imagination.
究竟长什么样子
You can look at it later,
要看回去再看
but right now,
现在看啊
it might be quite unsettling!
可是瘆人得很
What if we really
万一真的
summon it here?
招惹出来了半面鬼
Then we might not survive!
我们都活不成了
That's a valid concern.
也对啊
After your brother passed away, there
你大哥死了之后
was initially nothing at the incision,
原本切口处什么都没有
but suddenly one day,
突然有一天
the incision
切口处
started showing
竟然现出了
some of his own misdeeds.
他自己的一些罪状
Are you aware of this?
你可知晓这件事情
I don't know!
我不知道
I don't know anything!
我什么都不知道
Since you don't know,
既然你不知道
then accompany us
那就陪同我们
to examine the body.
一起去看看尸体吧
It just so happens that these misdeeds
刚好这些罪状
are not very clear to us either,
我们也不是很清楚
and you can
你跟我们一同前往
clarify a thing or two.
刚好能解释一二
-Guards! -My lord.
来人  是 是
No, no!
不 不不不
I really don't want to see it!
我就不去看了
That would be too horrifying,
那个场面太过恐怖
I truly can't bear to look!
我实在看不了啊
Besides,
更何况
that's still my own brother...
那还是我亲哥哥
Since he is your brother,
既然是你亲哥
you should go and see for yourself.
那你更应该亲自去看看
You've been crying out for justice.
你一直在喊冤
We are just investigating the case,
不过就是罪状而已
so there's no need to be so nervous.
不用那么紧张
Please...
那
I beg you!
我求你们了
I am seriously begging you!
我求求你们
I... I'll tell you!
我 我说
I'll tell you!
我说
My brother did
我大哥之前
some foolish things in the past,
的确干过一些蠢事
but he doesn't deserve this!
但是罪不至于斩首啊
When my brother was young,
我大哥年轻的时候
he had a gambling addiction
好赌成性
and lost all our family's wealth.
输光了家产
He later realized his errors and quit gambling.
后来他痛定思痛戒了赌
Then he started a small business
然后做了点小生意
and even made some money.
而且也赚了些钱
But lately, he had been borrowing money
可最近他又频繁借钱
and even mortgaged our land.
甚至抵押庄田
We suspect
我们疑心
he has started gambling again.
他又开始赌了
Who would have thought
谁知
he actually believed
他竟然信了
the words of the charlatan
邻居介绍的江湖术士
and spent all his money on some elixirs!
拿银子全部去买仙丹了
Because of this,
为了此事
I had a fall out with my brother.
我和大哥吵了一架
Before long,
不多时
the neighbor who introduced the quack,
那个介绍术士的邻居
Liu Zongyuan,
刘宗远
showed up at
竟径直找到了
Dafu's teahouse.
大福的茶楼
Well, look who it is, Liu Zongyuan!
好你个刘宗远
Gentlemen,
二位仁兄
please try to stay calm!
稍安勿躁啊
I'm not here
我此番前来
to provoke you,
并不是要触怒二位
but rather to discuss something important!
实则有事相谈啊
We have nothing to discuss with you.
我们和你没什么好说的
If it weren't for you
若不是你
introducing that quack
将那个术士
to my brother,
介绍给我大哥认识
would my brother have ended up
我大哥会落到
in this situation?
今天这副模样吗
How dare you even show your face here?
你怎么还有脸过来啊
Look at what you've done
你把他大哥
to his brother!
害成什么样子
He even sold all his land!
连家里的庄田全都卖了
How could you do something like this?
做出这种事情
Do you have no conscience at all?
你有没有良心
As for that quack,
那江湖术士
I only mentioned him in passing,
我也是闲谈间提及
as a curious tale to share.
当做奇人异事分享而已
I never imagined
万万没想到
Mr. Li would become so
李兄竟然沉迷到
obsessed that he would sell his land!
变卖了庄田
I deeply regret it!
我也是后悔不已啊
Now all I
现在我能做的
can do is
只能是
help him minimize his losses.
帮他将损失降到最低
These days,
这些天
I've been managing his business for him.
我一直帮他经营着生意
Also,
还有
I've managed to help him
他变卖出去的那些庄田
reclaim all the land
我已经帮他
he had sold off.
全部收了回来
It's now all registered under his name.
都是以李兄的名义
If you have any doubts,
你们要是不信
I can show you the documents as proof.
我这儿有字据为证
Dafu, so...
大福兄 这
So Liu Zongyuan was indeed a decent man.
原来那刘宗远是个好人
We agreed to meet in two days
我们三人约定两日之后
to share a drink with my brother
约上大哥喝顿酒
and encourage him to turn his life around.
好好劝劝他迷途知返
By the way, Mr. Ji,
那个 纪兄啊
I just remembered
我忽然想起来
there are some business matters
有些生意上的事情
I'm not entirely clear on,
不大明白
and I'd like to seek your advice.
想向你请教一下
Shall we step aside for a moment?
咱们借一步说话
Absolutely.
好嘞
Help yourselves, gentlemen.
那这酒二位就先喝着
We'll step out to discuss,
我们俩出去聊完之后
and then we'll return to join you.
再回来与二位会合
Excuse us,
二位
gentlemen.
你们先聊着
I understood that
我明白
they were deliberately
他们是故意
creating a chance
给我们两兄弟
for us brothers to be alone,
创造独处的环境
so I could have a heart-to-heart with him.
让我好好劝劝他
Here,
来
Kaixiang.
大哥
look at yourself,
你看你
what has happened to you?
现在都成什么样子了
You've lost so much weight in just days!
几日不见消瘦了这么多
From now on,
以后
don't fall for the
莫要再信那
quack's deceitful words.
术士的谗言了
Taking care of yourself
把自己的日子过好
is far more important!
比什么都强啊
Little brother,
弟弟
you don't get it.
你不懂
Mr. Yuan truly has extraordinary powers.
那袁仙人是真的有神通
He can summon deities to descend.
他能请神仙下凡
I've witnessed it with my own eyes!
这是大哥我亲眼所见的
Kairui, listen to me.
弟弟 依着我看
You shouldn't get caught up
你就不要管
in those trivial matters.
手边那些琐事了
Join me in pursuing immortality.
跟大哥一起修炼成仙
Imagine achieving eternal life!
长生不老如何
What deities descending,
什么神仙下凡
what eternal life?
长生不老
Those are just tricks to deceive people!
那都是骗人的把戏而已
Kaixiang,
大哥
after all these years,
我们这么多年
we've sacrificed so much, and you...
付出了这么多 你
How could you so easily believe
你怎么能轻易相信
in such nonsense?
这些呢
And still be so obsessed with it?
还沉迷其中
Do you think our parents
你对得起
in heaven would approve of this?
我们在天的父母吗
Do you think you can justify
你对得起我们
all the sacrifices we've made?
这么多年的付出吗
That's enough!
够了
You're the one being foolish!
你才是愚蠢
You don't even believe your own brother!
连大哥的话都不相信了
Could I ever deceive you?
大哥我能骗你吗
Since we can't find common ground,
既然说不到一块去
what's the point of continuing the subject?
还有什么必要继续呢
Kaixiang,
大哥
you...
你
After that,
再后来
I ended up imprisoned until now.
我便身陷囹圄至今
Waking up to such a scene,
醒来看到那般景象
I truly can't make sense of
我实在搞不清楚
what happened that day!
当日究竟发生了什么
Lady Yan,
颜令史
I think it's about time,
我看这时辰差不多了
we should get going.
我们也该走了
About time?
时辰
For what?
什么时辰
But first,
不过
you need to get changed.
你得换身衣服
Why did you bring me
你带我来这种地方
to a place like this?
做什么
I got some leads in here, of course.
自然是查到线索了
The top courtesan's schedule is hard to book.
这头牌的时间可不好约
let's enter.
赶紧进去吧
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
you are finally here!
你可来了
The private suite is ready for you.
来 三楼上雅间请
This way, please.
来 这边
This way.
这儿
Excellent, I am most joyous!
好 大爷今儿开心
Let's enjoy a few more drinks!
陪大爷多喝两杯
Please.
请
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
make yourselves comfortable here.
你们在此好生歇息
Xiu will be here shortly!
秀秀呀 马上就到
Like a dream, a fairy, suddenly fading away;
如梦如仙忽零落
where's the evening glow gone, leaving the screen empty?
暮霞何处绿屏空
Mr. Pan, aren't you something!
潘郎君还真是厉害啊
You seem to know people everywhere.
到哪儿都有你的熟人
It looks like
看来
you're quite the regular here, huh?
你也是此处的常客喽
I only come here for investigation,
我来此只是为了查案
nothing more.
绝无其他
Since Xiu is the top courtesan,
秀秀既然是头牌花魁
she must be gorgeous.
那一定很漂亮
I'm curious to see
我也想见识见识
the enchanting beauties of Gannan,
这甘南道的倾城美女
and how they compare to those in Xiang'an.
和襄安有何不同
"The lotus fades in comparison to your charm,"
芙蓉不及美人妆
"and the breeze brings the scent of jewels."
水殿风来珠翠香
In your poem,
公子的诗中
the autumn breeze wafts,
秋风骀荡
the aroma of the lotus fills the air,
芙蓉花飘香
yet even the dew-kissed lotus pales,
就连那含着露珠的莲花
before the beauty standing near,
都不及眼前的美人
the wind carries her scent,
风带来的美人香
more pure and clear.
比那莲花还要清幽
However,
只不过
who is this sentiment
公子的这番心意
of yours for?
是要赠予何人呢
Like a lotus, she twirls in her dance,
美人舞如莲花旋
a spectacle the world has yet to witness.
世人有眼应未见
Who this sentiment is for doesn't matter;
赠予何人不重要
what truly matters is
重要的是
the beauty is right in front of me,
佳人在面前
yet she remains unaware of my feelings.
却不知我意
Miss Xiu,
秀秀姑娘
please give me some leads
我让您帮我调查
on Liu Zongyuan.
刘宗远的事情
Where's the poem I asked you to compose?
我约的词呢
Rest assured, I'd never forget.
那潘某自然是不会忘
Mr. Pan's instructions
潘郎君的吩咐
Xiu has committed to memory.
秀秀亦是铭记于心
When Liu Zongyuan first visited,
那刘宗远第一次来时
he could barely cover the tea fares
连大厅的茶费
in the hall.
都是堪堪凑齐
However,
只不过
I'm not sure when it all began,
不知从何日起
but he has become quite lavish,
他变得出手阔绰
often insisting on my company.
常点名要我作陪
Let me tell you,
我跟你说
their family
他们那家人
is filled with fools.
都是傻子
I managed to trick them with
我不过几张手写的字据
just a few handwritten notes!
就给蒙骗过去了
His brother and brother-in-law
他那个弟弟和妹夫
really need a reality check.
更该吃药
Maybe they should invest in some elixirs?
要不也让他们买点仙丹
You're quite the con artist!
还是你坏 还是你坏
Liu Zongyuan
想那刘宗远
must have colluded with con artists
定是联合了江湖骗子
to seize other people's wealth.
侵占了别人家的财产
So it seems
如此说来
Liu Zongyuan is the biggest beneficiary
刘宗远是李楷祥死之后
after Li Kaixiang's death.
最大的受益者
Step by step, he had
他一步一步
encroached on the Li family's assets
侵占李家的家产
until he has completely drained them
直到掏空他的家产
and finally fled.
最后潜逃
He may have severed the head of the corpse
他砍下尸体的头颅
perhaps to
或许是为了
divert all the clues
把所有的线索
to the masked spectre,
都牵到半面鬼身上
creating panic
以此来制造恐慌
to mislead our judgment.
误导我们的判断
Xiu and Pan Chi
秀秀和潘驰
haven't known each other for long,
认识的时间也不长
so why does she
为何会对他
trust him so deeply
如此推心置腹
to share so much?
说出这么多事情
While you were watering the flowers,
适才姑娘浇花的时候
I composed a new poem.
我写了一首新的词
After the rain, flowers bloom so light,
雨后花开几朵轻
in the cool summer, they stand so bright.
清凉夏日试娉婷
Lotuses on the pond, unstained by dust,
池上芙蕖尘不染
tired of watching,
看厌
A butterfly, content and wild.
过墙小蝶好心情
Leaves shimmer in the breeze,
叶翠流波风浅动
a gentle touch,
柔捧
A fragrance wafts, so delicate and such.
清香袅娜袖边生
A graceful maiden with a coiled bun,
俏丽女儿螺髻绾
discreetly forms the style,
偷剪
a crimson hue, so fine.
嫣红一抹指尖凝
You two, make sure to
你们两个
keep this "gentleman" entertained.
好好陪一陪这位郎君
Greetings, beautiful young man.
见过郎君
You are...
这是
It seems the boss lady
看来这老板娘
is quite the veteran.
是老江湖了
She can easily see through
这女扮男装
your disguise.
可过不了她的眼
Here, beautiful young man.
来 郎君
Let me raise a toast to you.
敬你一杯
You've worked hard on your investigations,
平时探案都这么辛苦了
so it's nice to take a break.
好不容易放松一下
Drink up.
喝吧
I...
我
Lord Shen?
大阁领
What brings you here?
您怎么来了
Please, let me explain.
你听我解释嘛
We went to the Scent Pavilion
我们去嗅香阁
solely for the purpose of investigation!
真的只是为了查案
Those hetaera
那些男伶
were not summoned by me;
也都不是我叫的
I didn't even lay a finger on them.
我根本连碰都没碰
I trust you.
我信你
I'm not upset about that.
我也不是因为这个生气
It's just that in the future,
只是以后
if you plan to investigate at night,
你若是晚上出去查案
let me know.
完全可以跟我说一声
When I couldn't find you at home,
回府找不到你
I worried something had happened to you.
我还以为你出了什么事
I was called away unexpectedly.
也是事发突然嘛
Next time,
我下一次
I will definitely
一定会提前
give you a heads-up.
知会你一声的
By the way,
对了
have you managed to locate Liu Zongyuan?
刘宗远你们可有找到
He defrauded and seized the Lis' land,
他诈骗霸占李家田产
and he is likely the one
很可能就是
responsible for Li Kaixiang's murder.
杀害李楷祥的凶手
We've tracked him down.
找是找到了
Let's return and start the interrogation.
那我们回去便提审
But he's already dead,
已经成了一具死尸
so he probably can't provide any answers.
怕是开不了口了
Liu Zongyuan lost his liver,
刘宗远丢掉的是肝
and the liver
而肝
was likely removed from here.
便是从此处被挖掉的
All that laugh, like moths drawn to the flame.
诸生笑飞蛾扑火
But they do not realize that like mayflies,
竟不知身为蜉蝣
fleeting in life, they do not enter the cycle of reincarnation.
朝生暮死不入轮回
Moths that brave the fire do not perish,
飞蛾历火不死
but are reborn anew.
轮回重生
Man's guise, beast's core,
人面兽心
Guilt unescapable, from the start.
罪责难逃
Disrespecting the fire moth
不敬火蛾
brings disaster from above.
祸从天降
Not masked spectre, Fire Moth Sect again!
又是半面鬼 火蛾门
Liu Zongyuan
这个刘宗远
was someone who practiced martial arts.
是个习武之人
Look at the calluses on his palms.
你们看他手上的茧子
It appears that
这么看来
Liu Zongyuan
这刘宗远
was intentionally feigning
是故意伪装成
ignorance of martial arts.
自己不会武功
He was masquerading as a merchant,
做一个商人
while secretly committing murder,
暗地杀人
but later he was silenced.
可后来却被人灭口
Perhaps
或许
we're overcomplicating things.
我们都把事情想复杂了
There's a more straightforward way
推测真凶
to identify the true culprit.
有更简单的办法
Liu Zongyuan swindled
刘宗远诈骗光了
the Lis' land, forcing Li Kaixiang
李家的房产
to borrow money from everywhere.
令李楷祥到处借贷
Who suffered the most from this?
伤害最深的是谁
Li Kaixiang is dead,
李楷祥已死
and Li Kairui is imprisoned.
李楷瑞在狱中
So that leaves only...
那么就只剩下
Ji Dafu!
纪大福
Exactly.
对
I've always had a lingering doubt.
其实我一直有一点疑惑
Liu Zongyuan, with his forged documents,
刘宗远拿着伪造的字据
falsely claimed that
胡诌自己
he had helped Li Kaixiang
已经以李楷祥的名义
retrieve the land he sold,
帮他把变卖的庄田收回
and he actually managed to deceive Ji Dafu,
居然就能骗到纪大福
making him believe
让他相信
that he was a good person.
他就是一个好人
After all, Ji Dafu
纪大福大小
runs a tea house.
也经营着茶楼生意
Wouldn't he have doubts
这种无私奉献的戏码
about such a selfless act?
他心里不会打鼓吗
Either Ji Dafu is
要么纪大福足够天真
incredibly gullible,
容易相信别人
or...
要么
he never intended
他从一开始
to believe
就没打算相信
Liu Zongyuan's claims.
刘宗远的说辞
From the very start,
从始至终
he wanted to take revenge on Liu Zongyuan
他都想报复
for defrauding the Lis' wealth.
诈骗李家财产的刘宗远
Now that we know Ji Dafu is a suspect,
已知纪大福有嫌疑
why don't we
我们不妨
start investigating him?
就跟着他查一查
What are you saying?
你怎么说话呢
What do you want?
干什么你
Don't you push me!
你别推我啊
Out of my sight!
滚一边去
My lord,
大人
you have to help me!
你可得给我做主啊
They are being unreasonable
他们一行人不讲道理
and bullying me!
欺负我呀
We have important matters to attend to.
我们还有正事要办
Hands off!
给我松开
At least help me find a fair solution.
不管也得给我评评理
You should report this
遇到此事
to the authorities.
你应该去衙门报官
The governor will
刺史大人
surely see to it that justice is done.
自然会为你做主的
You are right!
对啊
I should report this to the authorities.
我应该去衙门报官啊
What am I even doing in here?
我找你们干吗呀
Who are you exactly?
你们究竟是谁
We're just returning to visit family and
我们一行人返乡探亲
have some important matters to attend to,
还有要事要做
so we won't take up more of your time.
就不多打扰了
Farewell!
告辞
Let's go.
走
We, the Delinquents,
我等异良人
are honored to meet Lady Yan,
见过颜令史
Lord Commander.
沈大阁领
Regarding earlier,
刚才发生的事
what was that?
到底怎么回事
I am Sun Tan, the leader of
在下甘南道地区
the Delinquents in Gannan.
异良人首领孙谭
What just happened
刚才那一幕
was merely an attempt to
只不过是想让三位
hold up the three of you briefly
滞留一会儿
to avoid Ji Dafu.
好与纪大福错开
We've been investigating a case
我们最近在调查一桩
involving usury,
放利钱的案子
and it has led us to Ji Dafu.
查到了纪大福头上
This individual is quite discreet,
此人行踪诡秘
and to avoid alarming him,
为了避免打草惊蛇
we had to resort to this approach.
所以我们才出此下策
we apologize for any inconvenience caused.
还请三位不要怪罪
No worries, no worries.
无妨无妨
However,
只不过
this approach is a bit too conspicuous.
这个法子太过张扬
If there were observant individuals,
万一在场有细心之人
and they happened to notice you,
留意到你们
wouldn't that expose your intentions?
岂不是就暴露了
You are absolutely right, Lady Yan.
颜令史所言极是
This time, we were indeed careless,
这次是我们疏忽
and we will be more vigilant next time.
下次会注意的
If I hadn't caught a glimpse of your token,
要不是瞥见了令牌
I wouldn't have realized
我还真没有想到
that you are the Delinquent.
你们就是异良人
The token of the Chief Inspector!
异良帅令牌
No formalities, please!
不必不必
You flatter me!
折煞我了
The token represents the chief's presence;
见牌如见人
this is a basic principle
这点规矩
that the Delinquent are well aware of.
我们异良人还是懂的
Rest assured, Lady Yan,
沈夫人放心
in the future,
以后
if there's anything
有用得着
you need from us, the Delinquents,
我们异良人的地方
we will do our utmost
我们定当全力以赴
without hesitation!
在所不辞
You just mentioned
你刚才说
that Ji Dafu is quite discreet.
纪大福行踪诡秘
Have you uncovered anything?
可是查到了什么
On the surface, Ji Dafu
纪大福表面上
is a tea house owner,
是茶馆老板
but in reality, he also operates
实则还经营着
an underground casino
一家地下赌场
and engages in usury.
兼做放利钱的生意
A significant amount of money
很多的钱财
flows through his casino,
经由他的赌场
being laundered,
做账
and then circulated to various places,
然后流转到各地
making his activities highly suspicious.
动向十分可疑
Are you implying
你是说
that Ji Dafu
这个纪大福
is likely collaborating with
很可能在帮着
a hidden mastermind to accumulate wealth,
一个幕后高人敛财
laundering illicit funds
把来历不明的钱财
through the casino?
经由赌场输送出去
This case has extensive implications,
此案牵涉面甚广
and as we follow the leads,
我们顺藤摸瓜
we've uncovered many
发现很多
officials from the Gannan region
甘南道地区官员
who are also entangled in this.
也混入其中
This is why we act alone, not together.
所以我们只敢单独行动
Are you three interested in
三位
investigating the casino as well?
也想一探地下赌场
You'll need to disguise yourselves.
还需要乔装一番
Do you all remember your roles?
都记住了吗
You are Sun Daniu.
你叫孙大牛
You are...
你叫
Liu Qingming!
柳清明
I'm Wan Er.
我叫万二哥
The three of us
我们三个
are merchants who
都是来甘南道
came to Gannan for business.
做生意的商人
It seems you've overlooked
你们好像忽略了一个
the most crucial point.
最重要的问题
What point?
什么问题
We are heading to a gambling den,
我们要去的是赌坊
and among you two,
你们二人
who is skilled at gambling?
谁精通赌博呀
That would be me for sure.
自然是我了
I assure you
我保证
I'll win so much that
赢得他们
they'll even bring out the land deeds!
连地契都拿出来
Welcome, gentlemen!
三位
This way please!
来里边请
Here.
这边
Wan Er.
万二哥
Once you're seated,
你们坐下之后
when the waiter brings the tea and snacks,
店小二上茶点之时
just make a subtle signal.
就做一个暗号动作
Gentlemen,
三位
this way, please.
咱这边请
Someone will escort you to the casino.
会有人带你们去赌场
I'll be undercover as a guard there,
我在下面当护卫
ready to assist you when needed.
到时可以接应你们
Place your bets!
买定离手啊
Halt!
站住
You three
三位
look unfamiliar.
看着很面生啊
Big!
大
Let's go, no dawdling!
快点 别磨磨蹭蹭的
These gentlemen seem a bit bored,
几位郎君闲来无趣
and they want to bet big.
想玩把大的
Just take them inside.
你把他们带进去就行
Sure thing.
行
Understood.
知道了
Follow me.
跟我走吧
Come on! Again!
再来 再来再来
Come on!
来
Keep it going, hurry!
继续 快
Bet big or small?
押大押小
Big!
大
Coming through.
借过一下
Big, big!
大 大
No regrets once the bet is placed.
落子无悔
Place your bets and leave it!
买定离手
I won!
我赢了
It's all mine, all mine!
都是我的 都是我的
Bet big, bet big.
押大押大
-Big, big! -Small, small!
大大大 小小小
Help me out here!
帮忙啊
Congrats, everyone!
恭喜诸位 恭喜诸位
One more game!
再来再来再来
This time, I'm betting big!
这把我押大
Place your bets and leave it!
买定离手
What stakes are we playing for today?
我们今天是玩多大的
Let's follow Wan Er's lead.
全听万二哥的吧
You play a few arounds;
今天你就来赌几把
if you win, it's yours.
赢了算你的
If you lose, it's on me.
输了算我的
Sounds good.
行
Then for the first round,
那这第一把
fifty taels.
五十两
Alright.
行
Big!
押大
Everyone, place your bets and leave it!
诸位买定离手
Big or small, place your bets and leave it!
押大押小 买定离手
Look closely,
看好了
fifty taels!
五十两啊
I'll go big!
押大
Everyone,
诸位
no regrets once the bet is placed!
落子无悔 买定离手啊
I'm betting big!
我押大
I'm betting small!
我押小
Something is off for sure.
果然有问题
One, two, two, five points, small!
一二二 五点 小
Congratulations to everyone!
恭喜诸位 恭喜诸位
Looks like your luck isn't great today.
今天你手气不好
Let Sun Daniu take over!
换孙大牛来
Today's not my day,
我柳清明
I must say.
今天手气确实不好
Daniu,
大牛
you are up!
换你来
My stomach...
我这肚子
It hurts so bad.
肚子忽然疼了
What's wrong with him?
这人怎么了
No, no,
不行不行
I need to use the restroom!
得上趟茅房啊
But,
不过
I'll wait until you
还是等你押完这把
finish this round.
我再走吧
Our boss, Wan Er
我们万二哥
doesn't want to bet small,
不想玩小的
he wants to go big.
想玩把大的
Exactly!
对
I'm curious how much you gentlemen
不知几位郎君
want to wager?
想要玩多大的呢
One thousand taels!
一千两
One round to determine the winner!
一局定胜负
One thousand?
一千
What, one thousand taels?
什么 一千两
Alright!
好
With such a hefty bet,
这么大的赌注
how about we adjust the payout?
要不然换个赔法
How about one to two?
一赔二怎么样
Sure thing!
自然可以
No regrets once the bet is placed.
落子无悔
One thousand taels,
一千两啊
I'm betting big!
我买大
-Open it! -Open it!
开啊 开啊 开啊
What's taking so long?
磨蹭什么呢
Hurry up!
快开啊
Exactly!
就是啊
Come on, open it!
开啊 你快开啊
Exactly,
对啊
what are we waiting for?
这等什么呢
When I was losing earlier,
刚才我输钱的时候
you were so eager to open it.
你开得比谁都快
Now what?
这会儿怎么着
With such a large bet,
这么大的赌注
shouldn't you make it quicker?
不是应该赶紧开吗
Exactly!
就是啊
Open, open!
开啊 开啊 开啊
Let's go, let's go!
开 开 开
What are you waiting for?
还愣着干什么
Open it already!
开啊
Right!
就是
Open it!
开啊开啊
Come on, let's go!
开开开 开啊
What's going on?
怎么回事
We've been waiting forever!
等这么久了
I won! I won!
赢了赢了
-I won! -Incredible!
赢了 好厉害
Gentlemen,
几位郎君
today must be your lucky day.
今天的手气可真好啊
How about this,
不如
since you are now on fire,
借着手气
let's have another round.
再赌一把
Our boss wants
我们的老板想
to meet you all personally.
亲自会会诸位
That's it for today.
不赌了不赌了
Tell your boss
你去跟你们老板说
that the silver we won today
今天我们赢的这些银子
is more than enough!
就够了啊
I've heard several
好啊
esteemed guests have arrived today.
听说今日来了几位贵宾
I am Ji Dafu,
鄙人纪大福
the owner of this establishment.
是这个赌坊的老板
Whether we gamble or not doesn't matter;
我觉得赌不赌不重要
what matters is building friendships.
重要的是交朋友
I've prepared some fine tea in the suite.
在下已在雅间备了好茶
I warmly invite you all to come upstairs
劳烦几位登楼
so we can enjoy tea and conversation.
咱们边喝边聊
Fine.
行
We are coming now.
那赶紧的吧
Xing.
六娘
Gentlemen,
三位郎君
it's a pleasure to meet you!
幸会 幸会啊
Come, come.
来来来
Please.
里面请
What's going on here?
干什么呢
Being so clumsy.
毛手毛脚的
You are going to scare my guests!
不怕吓到我的客人啊
Boss,
掌柜的
this man is no longer of any use.
这个人已经没用了
What should we do with him?
要如何处置
Why keep someone useless?
没用的人还留着干什么
Throw him out!
扔出去
Understood!
是
Winning big in
在我的赌坊
my gambling den,
敢赢这么多钱
not weighing the length
也不掂量掂量
of his own life...
自己的命有多长
It seems the tale of the masked spectre
看来那半面鬼
eating people's limbs while they sleep
趁人睡着
likely originated from the casino,
吃了胳膊腿的传说
where victims, having lost their limbs,
多半来自赌场里
dare not speak out
被砍去手脚的受害者
and instead
不敢明言
claim amnesia.
而谎称失忆
Apologies, gentlemen.
让三位郎君见笑了啊
My men can be a bit clumsy,
我这手下人毛手毛脚
and they seem to lack courtesy.
就是没个眼力见
I trust I didn't frighten you.
没吓到你们吧
You certainly startled me just now!
你刚才吓到我了
What happened to that man's arm?
那个人胳膊怎么了
How did it get broken?
怎么断了
Oh, it's nothing serious.
没事没事
It's just that man's arm was quite fragile;
都怪那个人胳膊太脆弱
a slight touch,
这一碰
and it snapped.
就断了
I can see that
瞧得出来
you gentlemen
三位爷
have won quite a substantial
在我的赌坊
amount of money in my casino.
赢了这么多钱
That wouldn't be right. Don't you think?
不太合规矩吧
We won it fair and square!
这银子是我们赢的
It's not like we took it by force.
又不是我们抢的
How can that be wrong?
怎么就不合规矩了
If that's the case,
既然这样的话
I won't waste any more time
我就不跟你们
with idle chatter.
多说什么废话了
I'll present you with two options:
我给你两条路选
either
要么
you play with me and
乖乖跟我赌一场
return the winnings,
把赢的钱还回来
or you can keep the winnings,
要么赢的钱你们留下
but you must leave behind
但得留下
a part of yourselves.
你们身上的一部分
Choose wisely!
选吧
I refuse to
你说的那两条路
choose either option;
我都不选
I'll keep the silver and my body parts!
我要银子也要身体
It seems there's nothing more to discuss.
那就是没得聊了
Boss, there's
掌柜的
someone outside wants to see you.
外面有人要见你
I'm busy.
我正忙着呢
Send them away!
打发走
The governor, Lord Mo,
来人里有营州刺史
is among the visitors.
莫大人
Keep an eye on them!
给我看好他们
Stay back!
走开啊
Lord Shen.
大阁领
Take them away.
带走
Understood!
是 是
Move!
走
Faster!
走 老实点
This is absolutely outrageous!
岂有此理
Establishing a secretive
居然有人敢在
gambling establishment
本官眼皮子底下
and resorting to trickery
私立赌场
right under my nose!
故弄玄虚
I only discovered while reviewing
下官此次查阅案宗
the case files
才知道
that Ji Dafu's wife, Li Xiulian,
这纪大福妻子李秀莲
was a victim of a
正是多年前
notorious rape-murder case
一起恶性匪徒奸杀案的
from many years ago.
受害人
And this case
而这匪徒
was precisely caused by her brother,
恰恰是她兄长李楷祥
Li Kaixiang, who failed to repay a loan.
借贷不还才导致的
The headless corpse case was likely
无头尸案
Ji Dafu seeking revenge for his wife,
多半是纪大福为报妻仇
using the rumor of masked spectre
借用半面鬼传闻
to cover up the killing of Li Kaixiang.
杀了李楷祥
Does Ji Dafu even
这个纪大福
acknowledge the existence of the law?
眼里到底还有没有王法
How could such a villain
这种恶人
have escaped justice?
居然让他跑了
Guards!
来人
Everything is going far too smoothly...
这一切都太过顺利
Relay my order immediately!
传令下去
Launch a citywide manhunt for Ji Dafu!
全城缉拿纪大福
Understood!
是
Lord Shen,
大阁领
Lady Yan,
颜令史
Your courage
今日
in venturing into danger
还要多谢二位深入虎穴
has solved this case.
才能一举侦破此案
Take your rest;
二位今日就好生休息
I will see to the rest.
剩下的交给我
Trust me,
相信我
I will certainly capture Ji Dafu
一定会早日将纪大福
and bring him to justice!
缉拿归案
The masked spectre?
半面鬼
He have slipped away.
竟然让这厮跑了
Shen Du!
沈渡
Kill me...
杀了我
His limbs' meridians have been severed,
四肢经脉都被挑断
and his face was flayed.
还被人剥了脸皮
To accomplish this in such a short time,
这么短时间内完成
he must be a seasoned criminal!
凶手只怕是个惯犯
What's going on?
怎么了
What happened?
发生何事
Biqiu has lost too much blood;
比丘他失血过多
I fear he may not survive...
恐怕他
Biqiu!
比丘
Hang in there!
怎么了
What happened?
怎么了这是
Masked spectre...
半面鬼
It was the masked spectre, right?
半面鬼是不是
I will not let you go unpunished!
我与你不共戴天
Why did you do this to my subordinate?
为何要这么对我的下属
Come at me!
冲我来
You should have come at me!
冲我来啊
Lord Mo,
莫刺史
please calm down.
你先冷静一下
Did you see his face?
你可有见到凶手的脸
-Biqiu! -Plea...
比丘 求
What do you wish to say?
你要说什么
Please...
求求你
End my suffering...
给我个解脱
Shen Du!
沈渡
Put me out of my misery...
给我个痛快
Gratitude...
谢谢
Biqiu,
比丘
rest assured,
你放心
I will treat your family
我定待你家人
as if they were my own.
如我家人
There's no need to blame yourself.
不必自责
In this world,
这个世上的恶人
there will always be wicked individuals.
本就是除不尽的
I understand this reality.
我知晓这个道理
It's just that...
只是
Witnessing it firsthand
只是亲眼看见了
is still too much to bear.
还是瞧不下去
Then let's stop watching.
不看了